hello and welcome to the neurodivergent
show with me emofolani I'm so excited
that you've chosen to spend your Friday
evening with us welcome you all
uh today I bring you good news I bring
you
um
I bring you Joy um I bring you testimony
from the autism Community but in case
it's your first time on the show
um let me tell you what the show is
about real quick this is where we
discuss all things autism all things
ADHD OCD and dyslexia it is the
neurodivergent show and Today's Show is
very special very dear to my heart today
we're going to be discussing the life of
um Dr Jason Ade
Dr Jason Ade
um it's such an inspiration big shout
out to tolu
um she had sent me a video on Instagram
the other day and I appreciate you for
doing that upon watching this video I I
just it was just hope upon hope upon
hope and I wouldn't be doing much of a
talk and I'm gonna let Dr Ajay um Dr
Ajay for more ADI I'm sorry for one of
these videos
um do some of his talking for us and
when we watch the video and come back
we're going to explore his life even
further it is the neurodivergent show
please go ahead and subscribe like and
leave us a comment below we're going to
be doing all of that taking all your
comments reading through exploring the
life lessons to be learned from Dr Jason
ade's story I'm gonna play his video
right real quick all right get there
take a look I'm completely out of my
depth
I'm struggling
I really want to quit
because
I've gone to University
alternative way
what matters more
to you
winning
or
getting across the line
I want to tell you about an alternative
way of winning
an alternative way
of being
finding a way to win and finding a way
to get across the line
facing adversity with a grin
this is my story
when I was three years old I was
diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder
the educational psychologist said to my
wonderful mother gifty
who I refer to as gif
your son has a hybrid of autism
called Global development delay and
Asperger's Syndrome
he's partially deaf in one ear you're
going to have to teach him to sign
now marathon is going to come up a lot
in this talk
because it's a really easy metaphor to
use
and in terms of endurance this was my
mum's first test of endurance
she could have felt I guess she was
dealt a bad hand
two boys 13 months apart my brother
Joseph and myself both autistic
tough times
but she embraced it
and that was the thing about gifts she
was wonderful she was amazing
she'd always say to me Jason
you are unique you are a wonderful human
being and you will do great things
and that's thing of repetition you hear
it over and over again and it's a
self-fulfilling prophecy you begin to
believe that
so
for seven years three times a week we
would go to speech therapy classes
doing the same speech therapy exercises
and algorithms over and over and over
again
there wasn't anything to suggest that
things were improving not one iota
but then
something happens
and this comes off the back of
educational psychologists and their
perceived wisdom
one being
your son is going to struggle to survive
in the real world
he's going to struggle to survive as an
adult or a child in the real world he
will need as much support as possible
during this period of seven years where
we're doing these phonic exercises
you do the same things over and over and
over again
and I love repetition I'm autistic I
really do love repetition very often I'm
telling the same stories as I've told
them the first time and everyone's
always looking at me as if to say
he's told that story about 50 times
but
on this particular day
it was a really special moment
it was a really similar one
everyone's backs were turned to in the
room so they weren't facing me
I'm in the room practicing these
exercises
I take my hearing aid out of my ear
and at the age of 11
I say my first word
hello
my mum stands and she says Jason do it
again say again
in disbelief
and so I say again
hello
it was a huge powerful moment
and the reason why this moment resonates
so much
is because it was the first time I
realized
that despite me having unfavorable odds
potentially if I worked hard and
persevered at something
I could convert the most unfavorable
odds into my favor
so roll on
what was a Helter Skelter
adolescence into teenage hood and I
become an adult I'm 18 years of age
um except I've just learned to read and
write so in many respects I've got the
keys to the world all be it with a
reading age of an eight-year-old but
we're cooking with gas it's it's at
least we're doing something
Step Into The Fray
Sandro Andre Sandry
an eccentric Brazilian Italian from
kodachuba
he turns around to me and he says
Jason
what do you want to do with your life
I humbly reply
but I'd like to work in the supermarket
so I can support my family and friends
he says Jason you can dream bigger than
that
I think we could get to University in
two years
we could take on the world and win
I look at him again and I laugh
and he says to me what are you laughing
at and I said it well with my modest
capabilities there's no way I can get to
University by this point I've learned a
thesaurus I've got a source I'm starting
to use words now I'm putting things
together it's great
and
there's always that one person for all
of us that brings us on a journey they
allow us to believe they allow us to
think outside of our own capabilities
and dream beyond measure
and that was a beautiful thing about
Sandra
so we get to University two years later
as he professed
fantastic great
however I get there and I'm completely
out of my depth
I'm struggling
I really want to quit
because
I've gone to University effectively with
a reading age of a 12 year old and I'm
doing degree level work
but something really Valiant happens
find out at 21
I'm going to become a dad
and that particular moment paralyzes me
with fear
completely paralyzes me with fear
and so I
accept this
as a situation and it gives me a reason
to persevere
the actual thing that becomes the iconic
image in my own mind
is having Taylor in my arms for the
first time in fact she was in my hand
she was in my hand and I remember
looking at him thinking I'm going to
give it everything I've got everything
I've got
okay that's Dr Jason our day ladies and
gentlemen and um he's autistic at this
time he's the youngest black professor
um that's been employed to Cambridge and
that's huge
um knowing that many universities like
that don't you know accept blacks to
begin with and then a black autistic
that's such a major major achievement
this is Dr Jason a day you heard him say
he couldn't speak until it was 11 if his
first word
hello
eleven
he couldn't read or write until it was
18 and now not only is he celebrated
worldwide he has two masters he has PhD
is married with kids he's doing great
with his life and when I saw this you
should have seen the joy that just swept
through me because for all parents of
autistic kids there is hope
right there is hope
Dr Jason Ade brings us hope there is
hope there is hope ladies and gentlemen
there is hope and I'm so excited
when I saw this video I was so moved to
tears because this is the fear of many
parents that are autistic they're like
oh my God
what about the future of my kid
will this kid ever talk with this kid
ever live independently you heard him
say that you know it was it was already
condemned like they already said there
is nothing for this boy you know is
going to be dependent on on an adult all
through his life and stuff like that but
he beats the odd
there is hope there is hope people there
is hope for the autistic child There's
Hope for the autistic adult so if you're
a parent out there and your kid is
autistic not speaking yet not doing some
of the things he should be doing don't
you dare give up on that kid don't you
dare say
um don't you dare listen to people that
say oh no his future is already doomed
no believe in your kid there is hope
we're going to be taking lessons from Dr
Jason ade's story
um is life as a whole I'm going to be
telling you more about some of the
things it's done and some of the things
that has helped him get to where he is
if you're just joining us this is the
neurodivergent show I am emofolami today
we are exploring the life of Dr Jason
adey who's an autistic
um we couldn't speak before 11 we
couldn't read or write before it's in
and now has gone on to do so many great
things including being
um the youngest black professor in
Cambridge congratulations to him on that
if you're just joining us I want you to
go ahead and subscribe to our Channel I
want you to leave a comment say hi to me
I want to say hi to you please go ahead
and say hi to me
please say hi to me I want to I want to
know how you do I want to know you know
just let me know that I'm not alone in
the studio okay go ahead and say hi I'll
give you a shout out and also make sure
you leave us a like okay like like like
like like thumbs up guys don't say I'll
do it after this you'll go ahead and do
that now all right we want to explore
the life of Dr Jason Aldi but before we
go into that for those of you that um
that that tuned in last week a caller
somebody called in and you know what she
said she said she had a testimony for us
her son
um who happened to be non-verbal till 11
um e e eventually eventually
um
became a surgeon
from non-verbal couldn't speak and then
a surgeon and there are tons and tons of
testimonies out there of many autistic
kids doing great with their lives so
today it's all about hope it's all about
um Joy it's all about
um
not giving up not giving in trusting
that I'm a Christian so I would always
say that the god that has put his kids
in your life
um is Hope is up to something and we've
got a few shout out here kedra says hi
to us Hi kedra Elijah says hi hi hi guys
hi thank you for saying hi to me I love
knowing that you're out there and you're
listening to me and I'm not alone by
myself so if you're here live with us go
ahead and say hi to us one of the things
I want to share with you um continuing
from what we discussed last week and
also exploring Dr Jason's life as
benefits of getting
um an early autism diagnosis and
um I'm going to be running through five
benefits actually and we're going to be
discussing them
um
in exploring
Dr Jason Addy's life if you heard him
there was something he said he said he
was diagnosed he was diagnosed at age
three
age three
one of the benefits of an early
diagnosis is the gift of an explanation
many people wouldn't know this last week
we said some reason why people do not
want to you know they do not want to get
a diagnosis is because they do not want
to label their kid
oh okay here hold on hold on um let's
hold that thought someone here is saying
she heard something we hear a car with
blinkers and Horn
huh all right can you are you still
hearing that though
it sounds very quiet
um in the studio but in case you can
still hear that maybe it was just a one
time off thing if you can still hear
that please let me know so we can know
how to troubleshoot and know where the
sound is coming from so if you're
hearing a car with blinkers and Horn
um let me know please so that we can
troubleshoot that thank you kedra for
that okay so we are discoursing the gift
of an explanation
at the age of three
Dr Jason Ade
God is diagnosis at the age of three and
so from the onset he just knew who it
was right
what parents don't understand is yes
there is the fact that autism can be a
liberal
but there is another fact which is
actually the one I think we should focus
on is autism can be a gift
it's an explanation
for a kids difference and many parents
that choose to get their kids diagnosed
early would realize that many times they
are kids will be better off for him why
because I'm telling you who you are
right from the onset I'm letting you
know that hey you're autistic when you
go out there people are going to treat
you differently but I don't want to hear
it from them I want you to hear it from
me I want you to know that you're
different and when you get out there
it's going to be so obvious but I want
you to know that you were different and
I love you being different and I accept
you being different and we're going to
work on it to make sure that your life
is as successful as God you know God has
called it to be but you know what accept
this gift because this is who you are
and I love that person you are and I
accept that person you are and I will
I'm I'm ready to I'm ready to introduce
the world to you
the gift of an explanation autism is not
a label or Autism diagnosis does not
necessarily have to be liberal as a
parent you can see it as giving your
child a gift like
many times
when adults
undiagnosed adults now you know the
world to seek their parents they notice
ignorance and things like that some of
the things we discussed last week about
you know why they did not get it
diagnosis so they grow up and they you
know they've always felt like you know
some I'm just different I'm different
everyone says I'm Different I just know
I'm different so they hear about autism
one way or the other online on this show
wherever they hear about autism and they
go ahead and get an Autism diagnosis and
you know the first thing they say
haven't studied autism they say now it
all makes sense
now my life makes sense
oh that is why I do what I do now I get
it now I know that you know many people
would have called him stupid or dumb or
decent but that's not who I am I just
happen to be autistic
and I wish I had gotten this diagnosis a
long time ago because my life would have
been different the gift of an
explanation the gift of an explanation
let's go to the second one
accessing resources after this one I'm
going to open the phone line so that we
can call in and you can share your
autism or just neurodivergent story with
us whether you know you know someone who
has you got your diagnosis early
um shout out to kijira that got a
diagnosis at 43 ADHD diagnosis that's
43. you can just tell us the impact of
getting an early diagnosis and if your
parents what you would do and what you
how you would advise other parents so
I'm going to be opening the phone line
so that we can call in and share
um the you know neurodivergence journey
in total and also go ahead and leave us
a comment okay let us know what it's
been like for you around you somebody
you know your own personal story would
like to hear from you
number two
accessing resources now I met with
someone sometimes ago and the person
kept complaining a kid has ADHD and she
was like it's just oh a kid has a kid is
has undiagnosed ADHD she knows but she
refused to get a diagnosis for her kids
because you know liberal and stuff and
she had her own reason but she was like
the kid is struggling is struggling in
school is struggling because you know it
takes some extra time to do his school
work it takes some extra time to do his
homework but they are not making
accommodation and the first question I
asked was have you gotten a diagnosis
for your kid and she was like no I don't
want him being labeled I'm like so
you do not have a diagnosis for your kid
that means that you are telling the
world that your kid is neurotypical and
so everyone including teachers in school
will treat your kid as neurotypical and
so you are complaining that you were not
they are not treating him as
neurodivergent
accessing resources when you get the
resources you get access to things like
speech therapy music my kids they do
music therapy speech therapy and you get
PT OT sometimes and many times these
things are free for ADHD ADHD has you
know they get to give them
accommodations in school they get to
give them extra time for examination
they get to give them extra time to
submit assignments all these resources
you can get to make a kid's life very
easy
one of our guests on the show the other
she came in and she talked about how
difficult her life was in high school
why because you know she was expected to
act like a neurotypical not a
neurodivergent she has ADHD and so it
was a struggle for her through school
and when she got to the University
School of Nursing actually
um things were a little bit different
because then she had gotten Her
diagnosis and so she could access this
resources now they were able to you know
make accommodations for her she could
take
um exam for longer hours they could give
her time to submit her assignment she
could you know she was she was able to
access therapists things like that that
is what you can give your kid but before
you're able to get your kid all that you
need a diagnosis because they need to
understand why your kid need all this
um all this resources so you know what I
just this is how I said I'm just like
let's just spear everybody the headache
let's spare everybody the trouble the
very hard life it's already hard for
neurodivergence now expecting everybody
to treat them like neurotypicals is even
going to be harder
so if you know that your kid is autistic
ADHD dyslexic OCD whatever it is
whatever form of neurodivergence I want
to encourage you today to get or seek a
diagnosis for your kid because it's
going to help your kid in the long run
okay so I promise that after this I was
going to open the phone line so that we
can all call in um for those that want
to call in
um and share their story I'm about to
put a number on the screen right now
let's take this one out real quick
okay I think we can come all right
keidra says let's take this one out
kitra says absolutely let's make it
easier for them I tell you I tell you
kidra and I feel like people would need
to hear from you tonight to talk about I
know that you know you'd come and talk
about you being diagnosed at 43 but I
think you could help people understand
the importance of getting an early
diagnosis because getting it at 43 you
know you talked about how your life was
before then and what your life is right
now
let's just save everybody the headache
let's get our kids diagnosed if they
absolutely need it thank you so much for
that
um see okay we can find it here oh
okay let me go ahead and do this
all right guys so the number to call is
-935-8734 the number to call is 817
-935-8734 would like to hear from you
would like for you to share your
neurodivergent story it could be autism
it could be ADHD what you have learned
so far what you've learned from Dr um Dr
Jason add a story and benefits of
getting an early diagnosis maybe you did
or someone else did would like to hear
from you the number again is
817-935-8734 and now we're going to be
going to the third one
um reason why you should seek an early
autism diagnosis is
oh let's stick this one out
we've talked about accessing resources
so we're going to go on to the third one
which is it helps others to understand
them better you see
before I accepted my kids were
neurodivergent it used to be kind of
weird right because people would see
them and they want to hug them and my
kids are like I know that's not
happening or my kids just walk away or
you know certain things my kids would do
I need to be so like awkward and I'm
like hug the key oh the adults or greedy
adults and my kids are like no or
something and they don't want to do that
and you know it's just awkward or
they're asking them questions and my
kids cannot say you know you know the
way a four-year-old should be able to
say something they couldn't put their
words together and it would be so weird
and it would be so awkward you know and
I'm like you know I need to be so
embarrassing sometimes because we're
forcing them to say it and the people
and people are like you know you don't
have to let them you know it's just it's
just weird you just have all this
awkwardness going on but as soon as I
was able to accept my kids are
neurodivergent now I'm the first person
to tell you I'm like when you meet my
kids my kids are not going to hug you
not because they don't want to but
because when they get into a new place
or they see new they want to explore a
little bit so the answer is when we get
into a new building or a new surrounding
they you know neurotypicals will see
people they want to hug and play with
people my own kids are different they're
so curious when they wanna when they get
into a new environment they want to like
see what's going on they want to see the
lightning they want to see how
everything has come together what's
working so they're going around and
they're looking at things and all those
kind of things and
initially that used to make me so like
worried like you know in Paras like oh
my God people would say they are weird
and stuff but now it's kind of different
because I'm the first person to tell you
now that when I get to this this my kids
are not going to hug you I mean they may
eventually come say hi to you but that's
not what's going to happen at first
they're going to explore their
environments they're going to look
around and then maybe when they're
satisfied with what they've seen and how
everything works and how the lightning
and sounds and everything how everything
works they're probably going to come and
maybe say hi to you and run away and I
realized that as soon I was or when
whenever I tell people that or whenever
I just told them a little bit about my
kid if they're going to be spending time
with them
when they met them it was actually easy
right because they kind of understood my
kid already from the explanation I gave
them
so they already had like this you know
this thing in their mind that says oh
the expectation you know I already said
the expectation so now it's not so
awkward when I get to when we get to a
place it's not as awkward anymore
because they already know that they're
going to go do their thing and I'm not
saying hook them or greet them or
something eventually everyone like there
is an understanding
so when you accept your kid as who your
kid is autistic
um adhda OCD dyslexic whatever it is
you're actually giving giving others an
explanation helping teaching others
training others how to understand them
and that's one of the reasons I started
this show I started the issue because I
wanted to I wanted the world to
understand my kids I'm hearing the world
for them and preparing them for the
world so by the time we all meet they
meet the world the world meets them it's
actually very easy like there is an
understanding the awkwardness is out of
it it's not like everyone has like why
are they acting this you know we already
know we already know so let's just get
that one out of the way and let's talk
about something else we already know my
kids are not going to do this you
already know I already know your kids
are not going to do it we get it we've
already settled that so let's just get
on to whatever it is we want to do
so if you're out there and you're
wondering and you're still saying should
I accept my kid Should I stick a
diagnosis for them yes you should
because when you do that you help others
understand them first you help them
understand themselves so you're helping
the autistic kid understand he's
yourself and then you're also helping
others understand them
the number to call again is
817-935-8734-817-935-8734 and go ahead
and leave us a comment let us know
um let us know what you think about what
we are discoursing
um let's know
um what you've learned from Dr Jason at
his life you know about his autism
experience let's know if you know the
success stories here and there you've
heard you know about people that have
that have become successful in their
autism Journey all right we have a
caller
hello this is the neurodivergent show
would you like to share your name and
where you're calling from please
yes this is kedra from Dallas Texas hi
kedra
Hi how are you fine thank you how are
you
I'm awesome I really like what you're
sharing here and actually I'm learning
so much because
um I have a very dear a person very dear
to me who has autism
um and is a child and we and we were
trying to decide whether or the parents
not me they're trying to decide whether
to get a diagnosis or not
and but we have access to all of what
seems to be the benefits in the school
and that you know in the early uh speech
therapy and all of that but I never
thought about it's good to have that
just and then to also share it so that
other people can understand because
you're giving you know I'm just gonna
say in America when kids come in the
door and they don't speak they just walk
past you or they sit down on the sofa
and they don't acknowledge anyone else
in the room you know the way I grew up
that was considered rude or
disrespectful and so I never thought
about what you're saying and I think
that's a that's I just thank you for
sharing that
I appreciate you for sharing your
thought with us and hopefully
um with some of the things we've
discussed we're able to help people
um understand the need to seek and
autism or you know a neurodivergent um
diagnosis but for the sake of those
who've not heard from you can you just
tell us a little bit about yourself your
diagnosis I know you've shared it before
but many people yeah yeah go ahead
yeah so so yeah I was diagnosed with
ADHD at the age of 43 and then uh
self-diagnosed as well actually I took
the assessment but self-diagnosed also
as a level of Asperger's so
um it wasn't until now that I can really
look back on my life and understand my
own life like it's allowed me to
understand why you know I I look at
um
the amount of times I was suspended from
school from fighting and for all of
these things and so now as I realized
that my understanding is different and
it's not about being smart because I was
smart but I I didn't the social skills
the the interaction with others those
are the things where I can see now that
I'm different so and what I've said for
most of my life to people is that my
brain doesn't work that way I would
always say that but I had no idea ADHD
or Autism or Asperger's or I had never
looked into those things I would just
say my brain doesn't work that way I
don't know you know but and and there
was always misunderstanding always and
so now I'm just very grateful to have
the knowledge and understanding and so
now at 53 I'm really delving into
understanding neurodivergence and how
well and it's such a spectrum it's not
one one or two or you know whatever that
we're all different even within the
typical uh the the typical part of
um
oh what am I trying to say
you know what I mean neurotypical
even within there there's differences
but as far as from a neural Divergent
standpoint we're all just so different
and I can appreciate it and I can learn
and study and as I do that I I learn
about myself you are such a blessing
kedra thank you for sharing your story
I'm sure you'll continue to share a
story to parents out there okay now that
you let's let's start before you leave
what advice you would diagnosed at 43
you sort out your own self-diagnosis
what advice would you have for parents
that are still hesitant I mean you were
through you went through this not
diagnosed and here you are 43 still gets
in your diagnosis what advice would you
give to parents that are still on the
fence wondering you know should I do
this should I not do this what do you
have to say to them from your own
experience
I would I would say to them you want to
give your child or your loved one every
opportunity to have access to whatever's
going to give them the best possible
life the support system and all of the
special things that they may need
um and so I you know from that place and
I understand people have very strong
feelings about it but from that place I
think if it were me uh and I were
deciding about my child I would do every
single thing
um to get that information today so that
my child could have that you know that
information
and that's a very different place being
where I am now after being diagnosed
later in life than where I was younger
even when I had my son you know when I
had my son
um you know I saw possibly there were
these traits but we didn't we didn't get
a diagnosis for him I had not had a
diagnosis for myself so we just back
then we just thought well that's just
what the teachers say because they want
them to be still or they want them to
behave or they want them but now even as
an adult with and I can say share this
with my son
um there are things that he deals with
now that I can help him with because now
I understand it and that and you know
that you know that's a little bit on the
ADHD so that you know you might be
dealing with this so I think it's helped
you know even my diagnosis and
understanding of it has helped him as
well absolutely beautifully beautifully
said well done well said you were such a
blessing and I appreciate you so much
for taking out time to share with us
thank you
for this and keep doing this this is
great work thank you I appreciate you my
dear says thank you
necessary I do that often all right you
just hurt kidris say she was diagnosed
at 4:30 she wished she'd done that
earlier she wished all parents would do
that so that you know no this is a this
is how I said you have to know that
you've done your part you've done your
best as a parent and you may think not
getting a diagnosis or not accepting
your kid as neurodivergence is doing
your best it's not you're doing your
best for you because if you were to put
your kid first put your pride your ego
the shame it's going to bring on your
family and many of the things we talked
about last week you know the everything
is going to do to you as a person not to
that kid you would realize that getting
a keto diagnosis accepting the kid
that's different is the best way to go
for that kid I was going to throw this
in okay now when I say it helps others
to understand them better I'm not saying
that so that you go on sharing your key
diagnosis with many people if you notice
many times I say my kid is
neurodivergent I don't even go into this
specifics I just told you a little bit
about my kid and if that's one way you
like that's one way to go you know so in
case you're still a little bit hesitant
because you don't want to use the autism
word the ADHD you know you don't want
that stigma that's okay get a diagnosis
or accept your kid has been
neurodivergent and when you go out you
tell them my kid is neurodivergent I
feel like by God I'm thankful I'm hoping
that that word neurodivergence comes to
stay as good right so when people come
or when there's something like oh that
kid is neurodivergent people are like
people are like oh we understand that
that kid is neurodivergent and that kid
may need extra accommodation I hope that
what gets to stay I hope we can get to a
party and say oh my kid is newer
Divergent so people can understand or oh
that person is neurodiverging and it's
okay it's like when women neurodivergent
we're not saying that weird we're just
saying that it's also a different form
of you know human a different way one's
brains right still equal to everybody
still everyone is still equal but we are
just different because our brain like
teacher said is wired differently so
help or understand that we wouldn't
think like you we won't understand
things like you we may take things more
literally than you guys do but you know
in we are still we still like you
um but just different a different
version call it version 2.0 if you may
be able to take a couple more calls if
you're able to call the numbers
817-935-8734 today we are discoursing
the life of Dr Jason adey we're
exploring his life some of things has
worked for him and why is the success
story that he is he is the youngest
black professor in Cambridge beautiful
achievements he's got two masters he is
um oh I have another caller let's take
this real quick
this is the neurodivergent show what's
your name and what you're calling us
from please if you'd like to stay
yeah my name is Terry hi hi welcome to
the news
yeah
um I saw the story of
um Dr Jason I was so impressed and
I mean I saw it some sometimes around
this uh this week I mean it really
brings home for so many mothers out
there that even though he's got a new
Divergent child
there's hope there is
um yeah you're talking about the issue
of diagnosis
I guess I I am one person that's been
very passionate about
um this particular topic and and that's
why I had to call him
um
I see that especially for husbands the
African Community
getting a diagnosis is something that
will plug over
we struggle with it
and I will ask a question
what's not getting a diagnosis is it
because of the child or because of
ourselves
that's the question we need to ask
Ashley because on dread
or 99 of the time
from discussion with parents I
discovered it's not because of the child
it's because of ourselves as parents
because we don't want people to know we
have an autistic job or because we don't
want people to know we have an ADHD
child or OCD child or something you know
because the child itself doesn't even
understand what is going on in his life
yeah or at least an adult possibly
don't understand how being an autistic
person is you know in the world
but you as a parent is the one that you
are trying to share you don't want
people to know you don't want to do I
mean I have a community of mothers
because I have a community of a
um
parents that have new Divergent children
that I join every time and I see them
discuss
the issue of diagnosis
and pardon me to say it's always from a
selfish point of view
it's always to the disservice of the
child
because you know that if you can get a
diagnosis for that child then you can
access resources for the chat and
inevitably making the life of the chat
better
so why not just do it
you know
um I also want to point out that the
benefit of having a diagnosis surpasses
the uh the disadvantage of not having it
so if you look look at the pros and the
cons
do the pros at where's the cons of
having to have a diagnosis
I could tell you that the time I got a
diagnosis for my son
I mean it was when my house was really
open to the gift of the child that I
have
to the extent that the diagnosis was
telling me I have a child at that time
he was around too but I have a child I
have a brain of a seven-year-old
you know in terms of
um some some some skills you know I
can't remember all the skills but he is
operating the level of the seven year
old and in terms of speech and social
yes that's when he has
the uh
he has he means of development that he
has you know it is still lacks some
level of development in it but if I
never had that diagnosis maybe I
wouldn't understand that okay that the
reason why my child starts to read that
18 months was because yes he's operating
in higher skills in certain part of his
there is that impact of his of his brain
of his life you know and then we're able
to work on that strength
so getting a diagnosis I can tell you is
the best gift any parents can give a
child
um forget about the Aesthetics I've
heard someone tell me I don't want my
child to be a part of the statistics
you you're not going to share it you I
mean you don't have to share nobody
knows that your child have a diagnosis
but the point is if the child wants to
go go to a school
that will require certain accommodations
it will be easier for you bringing out a
diagnosis and then the teachers when I
go into any sessions now with the
teachers I talk from a point of
understanding because I understand the
strength of my child yes and it's been
stated clearly
I've had to meet with parents who think
that their child is Autistic or that
child is ADHD
Enlighten them to get a diagnosed before
when before and after they get it
diagnosis they realize that child not
only have autism the child have ADHD as
well well you are just assuming my child
have autism or March I just have ADHD
where the child can even have the truth
you know and sometimes you even think
that the things that I do for my child
to make my child be better
you know as an autistic person you want
to follow the same path not knowing that
that might not even work for you yeah
diagnosis will help you know that you
need to quote the spot because this is
what your child needs I'll give you a
very Vivid example I have a um in my
community of mothers I have a a lady
would chat as autism
but she assumed that the child only have
ADHD okay so I I had to share some of my
social stories with her about how
um I had to use diet to help my son and
then she was following the same pattern
and she was complaining she never got
results she's working so I can see your
own child is this talking he's doing all
sorts of things but my child is not
doing and I keep asking have you gotten
a diagnosis she's like I'll get to it
I'll get to it
you know she she never knew
giving the shy child sugar
I I don't I I don't take away sugar from
my son because it doesn't have advanced
effect on him but having to give your
child what sugar is when the sugar
content itself but the fruits that
contain sugar just give him the chat a
banana make the Chinese behave
it's not bad on its own
banana is not bad on the board anytime
the chat is something that a food that
is that has sugar content the child
keeps running you know just can't stay
still
that you want to follow the part of
someone
diagnosis helps you to have a tailored
solution to whatever it is you want to
do
so I'm just I just want to appeal to
parents
I mean please
try as much as possible and getting a
diagnosis now it's not even so easy you
can it doesn't even come easy before you
get a diagnosis you're on the waiting
list for one year two years
because of so many you know the ratio of
a child that have autism is that between
ratio 1 to 44 or like before so even you
want to get in now it's not so easy to
guess
you can get for the chat the better and
Ellie diagnosis is key before now they
said that if he can do everything for a
child between the ages of one and four
years the child is most likely to
recover from autism
but now it is not the same
so if you can get the early diagnosis as
as early as possible I regretted not
having to have that diagnosis as early
as 18 months when the doctor was saying
oh he might be he might be you know
because of all of these things and
that's why I I got it even at three
years old and I I'm still regretting I
should have done this earlier
so thank you so much for allowing me I
guess I've not taken off your phone
thank you thank you so much Terry we
appreciate you thank you all right
Divergent show today we're discussing
the life of Dr Jason Ade was a
successful autistic autism story
um is autistic he couldn't read until it
was he couldn't talk until it was 11 and
he couldn't read or write until it was
18. he was learning how to read and
write by 10 and now it's got two masters
his PhD is the youngest black professor
um over at Cambridge is
um doing well with his life today is
thriving You know despite the odd and
we're learning from his life we're
learning
um early if you had us earlier from his
tedx talk he said something about
getting an early you know his mom
already knew that something was going on
so they sold out an early diagnosis of
course the diagnostician like many
diagnosticians had things to say see
about you know him not him not being
successful and living an independent
life but himself if you watch other
videos of his and I'd encourage you to
do that
his mom took it upon themselves to make
and then you know the people is met the
community
um that was around him they make sure
that he made a success of his life and
if you had heard me the third reason
we're discussing also reasons benefits
of an early diagnosis many of Dr Jason's
at this video you hear him mention
things about the support system the
support system the support system the
truth is if you do not accept or get a
diagnosis for your kid autistic kid now
let's let's just use the example of an
autistic kid how do you expect the
community to support them because they
don't even know what you're supporting
what you're telling everyone is my child
is neurotypical my child is neurotypical
but then it's weird because your child
is not acting like a neurotypical child
and so the support cannot be there
because you know there's all this
there's a lot of awkwardness going on
and so I want to encourage parents today
if you're still on the fence you know
diagnosis Dr Jason got his diagnosis and
he's doing great he's driving so many so
many our color called last week as soon
as I said you know many people even with
the autism level like people would like
to call it are doing great are doing
great so autism the name the the name
it's called is not is no more is no
longer a limiting factor for your kids
so go ahead and do so we're gonna run
through the last two reasons
um why all the benefits of getting an
early diagnosis real quick and okay
let's take this one out we've taken this
one and so we're going we leave kids of
boarding of masking now this is a very
big one what masking is is
a facade all right so we kind of pretend
so I'm
autistic for instance and I like
steaming
I like steaming like this or doing this
but at the age of five people are
looking at me weird and like don't do
that or my parents like stop that stop
that don't do that so I learned to count
myself right
I don't like making eye contact but they
said it's very good so what I've learned
to do that you know there's some things
that does not really come natural to me
but because
that's what the world wants or that's
what's socially acceptable I've learned
to hide myself I've learned to hide what
I know how to do now I'm copying orders
now I'm I'm asking I'm I'm trying to be
like a typical person most likely
because my parents did not get a
diagnosis for me or my parents did not
even tell me that I was autistic in the
first place so you know there's that so
and you know what happens many kids they
continue to mask and they mask and the
mask but it gets to a certain point
where they are no longer able to mask
anymore and that's where you get the
autism born out where many autistic
people go into depression they have a
lot of anxiety because they are just
tired of the whole thing and it happens
over and over again if you do not
believe what I'm saying you can go on
Google and you know or check on YouTube
and
research autistic bonell
I do not want my kids
to grow up to become depressed
if I can help it
so what do I do I try to I just I try to
just the key is to love and accept your
kid people the key is to is to let's
just you know Terry said the reason we
don't want to get the autism diagnosis
is because of us let's just let's just
leave out we are me being the moment
being the dad and just look at the kid
and say
okay this is the advantage of getting a
diagnosis this is the disadvantage like
Terry said the advantage outweighs the
disadvantage so I'm just going to get
you a diagnosis and and and and help you
understand that your your
neurodivergence and let's just see what
happens
and you know what you're doing for that
kid you're giving that kid a gift of of
of a lifetime because the kid
understands you're helping the kid
access resources
um you're also helping the kid prevent
future
now this is not a present because some
parents would think oh my kid is
thriving my kid is now in Europe because
my kid your kid you will get to the
Future and you will see what I'm talking
about and you will remember that you had
IMO folami on a on a podcast say
something about autistic born out
but if you get that diagnosis or start
relating and treating your kid that is
autistic is autistic then you're
preventing that for that kid in future
because many people like Dr Jason Addie
they got their diagnosis everybody knew
what we were dealing with we knew we
were dealing with autism so we got him
into therapy we got him into everything
he wanted to do his mom got him into as
many things he had a community he had
his support everyone we knew what we
were dealing with so it wasn't a problem
of oh maybe it's not or maybe you'll
outgrew it it was a problem of this kid
is autistic what can we do what can how
can we help him what are the things he
or she needs and everybody got into
action and everybody was asking and that
is why you have a success story today so
as a parent I'm encouraging you to
please let's leave out just leave out
you for a minute and if you understand
about getting a diagnosis this is one
reason why you should let's prevent
future autism borne out for kids let's
round on let's take um the fifth one and
then we'll round off
um
real quick here early intervention makes
all the difference that's just a summary
of everything we've talked about today
early intervention makes all the
difference I want to encourage you today
after the show upon in some links um
below the comments so that I'll put in
some links in the comments so that you
all can take a look at Dr
um Jason Addy's life and some of the
interviews is done with NBC CBS they're
very resourceful you're hearing or
excuse me you hear him say over and over
and over again early intervention I was
diagnosed I studied therapy at three I
started doing this I had people support
me early intervention early intervention
it makes all the difference it makes all
the difference how a kid will turn out
especially an autistic kid how a kid
will turn out
most likely will depend on how early the
parents intervene and that is the truth
if you have an autistic kid and you're
locking that kid in the room and you
don't want anyone to know that that kid
is autistic I am so sorry I have to be
blunt here I am so sorry for the future
of that kid because you were not helping
that kid in any way and sorry for being
blunt but sometimes we have to call the
speed a spade
you have an autistic kid you're hiding
the autistic kid from a diagnosis hiding
the autistic kid from everyone just
because you know you don't want the name
or you you were not helping that kid in
any way you are not
you are not
last week we had discussed the reasons
why you know you should you you don't
want to get another diagnosis we
understand we kind of get it I was there
honestly I was there somebody had called
me to remind me last week about how my
reaction was when she started telling me
about neurodivergence autism like I will
not hear of it I will not hear of it so
I kind of get it but in the long run I
can proudly say that I was being selfish
then that is the truth I was being
selfish then and now that I know better
I'm hoping you also can can rise and
let's put the needs of our kids first
and and get them and autism diagnosis
and if you're absolutely not going to
get your kid an Autism diagnosis that's
okay that's okay I'm not fighting you
but at least accept that the kid is
different your kid is not making eye
contact your kid is spinning in circles
your kid hasn't frequent nailed down
your kid is a picky eater your kid does
not like pop places is always screaming
doesn't like social interaction you just
notice that your kid is so different
from it just accept first accept that
your kid is different then build up
gradually to getting a dad now says
let's take this last comment before we
leave
I couldn't consider it could be both
until now thanks caller Kiger is
thinking I'll call Atari that says it
could be both many times autism usually
you have kids that are just autistic but
many times you have kids also they're
autistic ADHD you heard him say I'm
sorry please excuse me I know what's
going on with my voice today you heard
Dr Jason Addy say he was autism and
Global developmental delay to diagnosis
or it's into it's it's a form of autism
Global developmental delay and there are
so many forms of autism and many times
you have what many kids that are
autistic would also have an ADHD
diagnosis or some kind of diagnosis
anyway that's our show tonight to
quickly
um recap what we've discussed all
evening we've discussed explore Dr Jason
our day's life was also giving you
benefits of getting an early autism
diagnosis or an early diagnosis you know
for child
um as you may we've talked about given
the key the gift of the gift of an
explanation was saying we can access
resources we're saying you can help
others understand your kid was saying
that we can
um relieve the key the burden of masking
in future and prevent possible future
autism borne out and we'll also say
early intervention can make all the
difference and I hope with this few
points you can now decide to start
accepting your kid as neurodivergent or
getting and or getting them a diagnosis
yes it's exhausting caterer says it's
existing I want to appreciate everyone
who's called into the show today thank
you so much KJ you're such a blessing
thank you tari thank you for sharing
your you know your experience with us we
appreciate you you all have blessings I
want to thank everyone that has caught
that has texted sent a comment
um appreciate you please go ahead and
subscribe right now don't wait because
if you wait you're not going to do it
subscribe and like like like like share
this video and until next week when I
come your way again thank you so much my
name is IMO folame I will see you 7 PM
next week Live on YouTube bye-bye